Joseph Cornell
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Cornell's source material is largely comprised of files of newspaper and magazine clippings, cutouts, notes, writings, book excerpts, photostats (or stats), prints, postcards, art reproductions, and other printed material. Some files are devoted to people (ballerinas, actresses, singers, artists, and writers) and topics (astronomy, romantic and modern ballet, birds, films, literature, music, plants, and science, among others). Other files relate to specific art works, "explorations," publishing projects, and exhibitions. Source material documents Cornell's preoccupation with certain individuals (past and present), events, subjects, and motifs; the development of some of his major "explorations" and their influence on his various artistic and commercial projects; and his work on certain box constructions and collages, publishing ventures, and exhibition catalogues. Source material also sheds light on Cornell's efforts to gain access to the past; his interest in the symbolism of images and objects; the linkages he found between seemingly unrelated things; and the connections between his many creative endeavors.
Ephemera and artifacts include various objects, mementos, and items of memorabilia, some of which were accumulated by Cornell (in much the same way that he collected his source material) and some of which are of uncertain origin. For Cornell, items such as these were not merely inanimate objects, but were instead evocative of past worlds and capable of bringing the past into the present (an idea which he often expressed in his diaries as the "metaphysique d'ephemera"). He seems to have used some of these items in a layout he designed for Good Housekeeping. Other items may have been used as source material for some of his box constructions.
The collection also houses photographs of Cornell, his family, art work, other artists, and friends, as well as photographs taken by various individuals and publicity photographs from the New York City Ballet. Also found are scattered works of art, including collage fragments and Rorschachs (or ink blot drawings) by Cornell, collages by Cornell's sister, Betty Cornell Benton, on which he collaborated, and a box by Christine Kaufman, which was a gift to Cornell. The books in the collection most likely comprise the remainder of Cornell's library, which was transferred to the Joseph Cornell Study Center, and include some that seem to have belonged to his sister, Betty. Printed material includes various publications and clippings collected by Cornell apart from that which he collected as source material. Writings about Cornell include an article by the poet, Mina Loy, and copies of various theses, presentations, and articles by graduate students in art history received by Benton (who assisted them in their research).
The Joseph Cornell Estate Papers consist of correspondence relating to Betty Cornell Benton's administration of the part of Cornell's estate for which she was responsible and legal documents relating to her various legal disputes with the executors of the estate, as well as a limited amount of printed material, some of which was originally accumulated by Cornell and subsequently shared with Benton, and miscellaneous papers belonging to Benton and their mother, Helen S. Cornell. Estate Papers provide insight on the exhibition and sale of Cornell art works after his death; the disposition of his belongings (including art work, papers, books, records, and source material); and Benton's efforts to foster and safeguard the memory and legacy of Cornell. The Robert Cornell Papers include correspondence, writings, art works, photographs, printed material, and scattered financial and personal records, documenting the full and creative life Robert led despite being confined to a wheelchair. Their inclusion in the collection suggests the family's effort to foster Robert's memory.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into eleven series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1918-1972, 1975 (Box 1; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1909-1982 (Boxes 1-5; 4.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Diaries, 1941-1973 (Boxes 6-10; 5 linear feet)
Series 4: Source Material, 1804-1972 (Boxes 11-18, 25-28, OV 29; 8.5 linear feet)
Series 5: Ephemera and Artifacts, 1858-1946 (Boxes 18, 23; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1905-1972 (Boxes 18, 28; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 7: Art Works, circa 1966-1971 (Boxes 19, 23; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 8: Books and Printed Material, 1806-1968 (Boxes 19, 23; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 9: Writings about Cornell, 1950, circa 1975-1980 (Box 19; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 10: Joseph Cornell Estate Papers, circa 1911, 1944-1986 (Boxes 19-22; 3.5 linear feet)
Series 11: Robert Cornell Papers, 1924-1965 (Boxes 24, 28; 0.4 linear feet)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Assemblage (Art); Found objects (Art); Art, Modern -- 20th century -- United States; Celebrities; Assemblage artists -- New York (State) -- New York
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Works of art
Names:
Benton, Elizabeth Cornell; Cornell, Robert
Provenance
The Joseph Cornell papers were donated and microfilmed in several installments from 1974 to 1989 by Joseph Cornell's sister, Betty Cornell Benton. Most, but not all, of the correspondence, which was loaned for microfilming in 1974, was subsequently donated in 1989. Additional material was donated in 2004 by the Joseph and Robert Cornell Memorial Foundation.
Separated Material
The bulk of Cornell's source material resides in the Joseph Cornell Study Center, Smithsonian American Art Museum, along with his library and record collection. Cornell's sister, Betty Cornell Benton, donated a portion of this material directly to SAAM (then known as the National Museum of American Art), occasioning the creation of the Study Center circa 1978. The bulk of the source material and library that she donated to AAA, including approximately 66 linear feet of three-dimensional and non-textual source material and 50 linear feet of books, was transferred to the Study Center in 1994 and 1995.
Originals of loaned material returned to the donor after microfilming include: some unidentified and miscellaneous correspondence; significant correspondence between Joseph Cornell and Helen S. Cornell; significant correspondence between Helen S. Cornell, family members and others; and some of Joseph Cornell's family correspondence and general correspondence from the Robert Cornell papers. The loaned material is available on microfilm reels 1055-1058 but is not described further in the Series Descriptions/Container Listing of this finding aid.
Related Material
The Archives holds several collections of different provenance that relate to Joseph Cornell, including the small collections of Allison Delarue (comprised of two letters from Cornell, available on reel 2803), Muriel Streeter Schwartz (comprised of two letters from Cornell, available on reel 4283), Wayne Andrews (comprised of letters from Cornell and printed material), and Marion Netter (comprised of items received from Cornell). In addition, photographs of Cornell can be found amongst the Hans Namuth photographs and papers. Also found within the Archives is a transcribed interview of Cornell's sister, Elizabeth Cornell Benton, conducted on April 21, 1976 as part of the oral history program.
Restrictions on Access
Use of the original papers requires an appointment.
Alternative Forms Available
The bulk of the collection was digitized in 2006 and 2009 and is available online via AAA's website. Duplicate material and ephemeral artifacts have not been digitized. Other material not digitized includes printed material such as books, magazines and exhibition catalogs for artists other than Cornell; typically only covers, title pages, and/or relevant pages of these items have been digitized.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1918-1972, 1975, Series 1:; (box 1; 0.8 linear feet)
  Series consists of material relating to some of Cornell's personal and professional dealings apart from his more artistic activities and shedding light on some different aspects of his biography. Included are: a school paper on Harry Houdini and a program from Cornell's days as a student at Andover; miscellaneous family papers (such as typescripts of Helen S. Cornell's writings as a child, a baptism notice for Robert Cornell, and Betty Cornell Benton's notes on family history); various personal papers (including Cornell's psalm book, some notes and jottings exchanged between Cornell and his family, and papers such as notes, correspondence, exhibition announcements, dream writings, ink blot drawings, and other material, which may have been those in his desk at the time of his death); official documents (such as copies of Cornell's birth and death certificates, and social security cards); address books; scattered business records (such as notes and correspondence with galleries, including the Egan Gallery, Stable Gallery, Richard Feigen Gallery, and Robert Schoelkopf Gallery, regarding consignment and sales of art work); scattered financial records (such as notes on income and expenses, receipts, and income tax returns); scattered legal records regarding the estate of Helen S. Cornell; and notes (including copies of Cornell's notes on art work and his "Rationale" most likely collected by Benton, his notes on the Bebe Marie doll, and his notes to his family in case of his death). Related material can be found amongst Cornell's estate papers.
  Material is, for the most part, arranged into files according to format or documentary type. Files are arranged alphabetically.
  The bulk of this series has been scanned with the exception of routine financial records and receipts.
  - Address Books, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Address Books, Notes, 1968-1972, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Antiques, 1954-1957, 1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Birth and Death Certificates (copies), 1970, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Business Records, Correspondence with Galleries, 1951-1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Business Records, Miscellaneous, 1962-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Family Papers, Miscellaneous, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Financial Records, Income and Business Expenses, 1947-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Financial Records, Receipts, 1951-1971, undated, (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Financial Records, Income Tax Returns, 1951-1952, (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Financial Records, Household Expenses, Telephone, 1967-1970, (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Last Will and Testament, Clippings, 1960-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Last Will and Testament, Notes and Writings, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Legal Records, Re: Estate of Helen S. Cornell, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Notes on Bebe Marie Doll, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Notes to Family (in case of death), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Notes on Art Work and "Rationale" (copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Personal Papers, Psalm Book, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Personal Papers, Notes, 1957-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Personal Papers, Calendar, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Personal Papers, Miscellaneous, 1971-1972, undated, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 25-29)
  - Red Cross Blood Donor Certificate, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Social Security Cards and Information, 1937, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Student Papers, 1918, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Correspondence, 1909-1982, Series 2:; (boxes 1-5; 4.2 linear feet)
  Series is comprised of Cornell's personal and professional correspondence, primarily consisting of letters, postcards, and greeting cards to Cornell from family, friends, artists, dealers, collectors, galleries, museums, admirers, "helpers," and charitable institutions. Also included, to a lesser extent, are letters between and amongst other members of the Cornell family. While Cornell did not usually make copies of his outgoing correspondence, he often wrote various versions of a letter. Several examples of these can be found amongst his correspondence, though it is unclear whether or not they represent letters that were actually sent. Files also include notes and printed material that pertain to various (often notable) individuals and/or institutions. Though most likely not actual correspondents, these individuals and institutions were of interest to Cornell in one way or another, which presumably led him to collect this material. Based upon this collecting activity, there is some overlap between correspondence and source material. Correspondence relating to Cornell and his artwork can be found amongst his estate papers.
  In general, the correspondence is heavily annotated by Cornell's sister, Betty Cornell Benton, who prepared his papers for donation to the Archives. In her annotations, Benton often supplies the last name of the correspondent and sometimes the date of the letter when these are not provided. Other times, she provides information about or commentary on the correspondent and his/her relations with Cornell.
  According to some of Benton's annotations, it seems likely that Cornell may have originally maintained some, if not all, of his correspondence in chronological files. At some point, correspondence was organized alphabetically according to the surname of the correspondent or name of institution. It is not clear whether this was carried out by Cornell, his sister, or someone in the Archives. The existing alphabetical organization has been maintained since, with so many undated letters, it would be impossible to reconstruct a meaningful chronological order.
  In the existing arrangement, general correspondence, family correspondence, and greeting cards were maintained separately in distinct groupings of files. Based upon this, the Correspondence series is arranged as three subseries:
  2.1: General Correspondence, 1909-1982
  2.2: Family Correspondence, 1909-1977
  2.3: Greeting Cards, 1956-1972
  This series has been scanned in entirety.
  - General Correspondence, 1909-1982, 2.1:
    Subseries consists of correspondence between Cornell and friends, artists, dealers, collectors, galleries, museums, admirers, individuals whom he admired or with whom he was especially preoccupied, "helpers," and charitable institutions. Included are letters (in some instances, with photographs or poems enclosed), postcards, and greeting cards, as well as some art work, three-dimensional objects, and artifacts. Also included are some notes and printed material, such as newspaper and magazine clippings, pamphlets, brochures, publications, and publicity material, pertaining to individuals, institutions, and/or topics in which Cornell had a particular interest.
    Correspondence documents some of Cornell's activities involved in creating his art work, such as his practice of using multiple copies of a single image in many of his works (as in a letter from John Allen referring to Cornell's order for multiple prints of a Loie Fuller image); his early attempts to advertise his art work (as in letters from the Blaker Advertising Agency, Columbia Records, Inc., and N. W. Ayer and Son); and his later, oftentimes hesitant, transactions with galleries and dealers, including Irving Blum, Charles Egan, Richard Feigen, Julien Levy, Robert Schoelkopf, and Eleanor Ward (See also Series 1). Correspondence relates to the sale of his art work to galleries and individual collectors, and the exhibition of his art work in museums, including the Cleveland Museum of Art, Guggenheim Museum (See Diane Waldman and Tom Messer), Pasadena Art Museum, and Whitney Museum (See also John Baur).
    The positive reception of Cornell's art work is documented in many letters from admirers (including poet, Paul Carroll, who wrote two poems about Cornell's art work, the Fourth Grade Class at Murray Avenue School, actress, Eva Marie Saint, and author, Glenway Wescott, among others). The critical reception of Cornell's art work is documented in the many letters from people who have written or express interest in writing an article about Cornell (including Howard Griffin from Art News, David Bourdon from Life magazine, and Brian O'Doherty, author of American Masters: The Voice and the Myth, among others).
    Correspondence also concerns some of Cornell's major "explorations," including ones on the singers, Maria Malibran and Giuditta Pasta (as in letters from the English scholar, Richard Coe), and the ballerina, Fanny Cerrito (as in letters from Lillian Moore). Correspondence relates to his other research and collecting activities and includes numerous letters responding to his requests for information and/or material from institutions, such as the Harvard College Library, dealers, such as C. and I. K. Fletcher, and individuals, such as Marian Hannah Winter.
    Correspondence documents Cornell's preoccupations with certain dancers (such as Allegra Kent, Tanaquil LeClerq, and Tamara Toumanova), actresses (such as Lois Smith), artists (Lee Bontecou), and other young women; his relationships with other artists, both young and established, including Piero Dorazio, Ray Johnson, Hubert Kappel, Roberto Matta Echauren, Dorothea Tanning, and Pavel Tchelitchew, among others; and his friendships and shared interests with individuals, such as Wayne Andrews, Charles Henri Ford, Parker Tyler, Donald Windham, and Marian Hannah Winter (their letters often entailing an exchange of ideas on topics such as literature, music, dance, art, and the pleasures of collecting). Correspondence also documents his generosity (in terms of gift giving) toward his friends (and their children) and individuals whom he admired (as in letters and notes of thanks for gifts of art work from Valerie Adams, George Bennette, Lee Bontecou, Susan Sontag, Jessica Tandy, and Tamara Toumanova, among others); and his generosity toward institutions providing public services to the less fortunate (as in letters acknowledging and expressing gratitude for donations from the New York Institute for the Education of the Blind and the Bedside Network, among others).
    General correspondence is arranged in files according to correspondent and then alphabetically according the surname of the individual or the name of the institution. Items are arranged in rough chronological order within each file. When only a few items (typically less than three) are associated with a correspondent, these are arranged into general alphabetical files. Unidentified and miscellaneous items are arranged into files at the end of the subseries.
    - Adams, Valerie, 1942-1959 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Andrews, Wayne and Lisa, 1947, 1965-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Ashbery, John, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Ashton, Dore, 1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - A, 1937, 1945, 1955-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Baur, John (See also Whitney Museum), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Beckman, Julie, 1955-1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Bennette, George and family, 1953, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Bergman, Edwin, 1959, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Blum, Irving (Ferus Gallery), 1959, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Bontecou, Lee, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Brandon, Baby (Mary Hopkins), 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Brown, Harriet and Bob, 1964-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Brown, Jo, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Bruno, Phillip (Staempfli Gallery), 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Burckhardt, Rudy, 1952-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - B, 1946-1972, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 49-51)
      Includes letter from Stan Brakhage.
    - Campbell, Sandy, 1948, 1956-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
      Includes photographs of actress Lois Smith and hairpins of actress Lilian Gish.
    - Carrithers, Dorcas, 1967, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Cleveland Museum of Art, 1966, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Couch, Lucile, 1967-1969, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Coulter, Dorothy, 1962-1969 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - C, 1925, 1949-1972, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
      Includes letters from: Xenia Cage, Paul Carroll (with two poems inspired by Cornell's art work), William and Noma Copley, and Cornell University.
    - De Maria, Susanne, 1963-1973, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - De Maria, Walter, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Consists of copies of correspondence between De Maria, Jan van der Marck and Marcel Duchamp (concerning the exhibition "Art by Telephone") and a photograph which constitute a work by De Maria called Chicago Project, 1968.
    - Delarue, Allison (See also Series 9), 1943-1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Dorazio, Piero and Virginia (See also Series 4), 1953-1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Duchamp, Marcel and Teeny, 1955-1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Includes Cornell's writing about a dream he had of Duchamp, and a version of a condolence letter to Duchamp's wife.
    - D, 1943-1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Includes letter from D'Arcy Galleries.
    - Eastman, Lee and family, 1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Egan, Charles, 1950-1951, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Ehrich, Jo Ann, 1969-1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Ekstrom, Arnett and Parmenia, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Engdahl, Leonore, 1966, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - E, 1949-1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Feigen, Richard, 1959-1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Fine, A.M., 1970 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Ford, Charles Henri, 1939-1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Includes pencil drawing by Tchelitchew on the back of a card from Ford.
    - Ford, Ruth 1969-1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Fried, Rose, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - F, 1955-1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Gablik, Suzi, 1961, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Gagner, Robert, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Garson, Inez, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Goodman, Trudy, 1965-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Graham, Susan 1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
      Includes ink blot drawings by Cornell.
    - Griffin, Howard, 1956-1957, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Grinstein, Elyse, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - G, 1948-1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
      Includes letter from David Gahr.
    - Hadley, Leila, 1965, 1970-1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Halper, Ed, 1967-1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Hammond, Paul, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Hanson, Elizabeth, 1966-1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Hodes, Barnet, 1955-1957, 1971-1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Hussey, Howard, 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - H, 1945-1972, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 38-39)
    - I, 1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Javitz, Ramona, 1946-1964 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Jean, Marcel, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Johnson, Ray and friends, 1966-1971, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 43-44)
      Includes illustrated letters, illustrations, and collages by Johnson.
    - Judreik, Sonia, 1963-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - J, 1956-1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Kappel, Hubert and Anne, 1947, 1953, 1965-1972 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Kent, Allegra, 1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
      Most of the material was returned to Kent per Cornell's request, according to a note by Benton; however, some notes and photographs remain.
    - Kesl, Leonard, 1969-1972, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 49-51)
      Includes ink drawings by Cornell.
    - Kirschenbaum, Carol, 1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Kreger, Nancy, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - K, 1954-1972, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-2)